<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[rapuhotelli]]></title><description><![CDATA[a strange diary and some stories for another time]]></description><link>http://rapuhotelli.net</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Apr 2018 19:18:42 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Priority queue]]></title><description><![CDATA[Being able to achieve  flow  states is one of the most enjoyable parts of my line of work. I love doing stuff with passion and genuine…]]></description><link>http://rapuhotelli.net/2018/priorities/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://rapuhotelli.net/2018/priorities/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Apr 2018 19:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Being able to achieve &lt;em&gt;flow&lt;/em&gt; states is one of the most enjoyable parts of my line of work. I love doing stuff with passion and genuine interest. However, a recent encounter taught me a lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suddenly it didn’t seem like I could get anything done. I was unsatisfied with my work and I was starting to get a bit worked up about it. I take my work quite seriously and me getting frustrated and overly self-judgemental is bad times all-around. I even wrote about &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/evaluation&quot;&gt;my recent trip&lt;/a&gt;, though at the time I didn’t know these were related. Now I feel like deleting that post because it’s a bit crazy, but I’m leaving it as a reference and a reminder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had just started a new project at a new working environment, hoping to solve my challenges with a breath of fresh air when it suddenly struck me. I called a friend and met him later that day to… stock me up. Weekend came and went and the following Monday and Tuesday were the most enthusiastic and productive (or so it felt – never mind what was actually achieved) days in the last two months. How could I have been so stupid?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course it was nicotine. I even wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/health&quot;&gt;grand declaration&lt;/a&gt; about my ambitions. Taking on the stress of having to prove myself to my peers, my clients and whoever the fuck, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; at the same time trying to tackle the effects of physical chemical withdrawal was a moronic idea. My grand plans still stand, mind you – the timing was just the worst possible. To my defense, when I started on my grand quest of dropping nicotine I didn’t know how my work would end up being and to that end the levels of self-loathing remained undefined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels silly but you have to be honest with things like this. The problem can be summarized into two choices:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take a hit to productivity and start fighting with anxiety while trying to heal my nicotine addiction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go on like always and keep using nicotine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can say anything but to me the choice is obvious. I’m in no position to bargain yet. I’m at the top of my world and I will not risk it for mundane issues like health ;) I have never been happier and nicotine addiction is a small price to pay. I will wait for maybe half a year, or however long it takes for me to be satisfied with my daily results, and then try again. I know I will succeed. It’s not about succeeding in it or not as I’ve done it before, I just need a… mentally safe environment to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile I can work on my other promises. Summer is coming and next weekend I’m gonna clean and oil my bike and take it for a test ride. Tomorrow a gym is opening literally downstairs from work and thus I’m out of any possible excuses. I’m expecting great things from this summer.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Fairy tales in 2018: Racism, Populism and Social Media]]></title><description><![CDATA[I was longing for something to smash my spare time on when I saw one of my favourite youtubers playing an interesting new video game. I was…]]></description><link>http://rapuhotelli.net/2018/ni-no-kuni-2/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://rapuhotelli.net/2018/ni-no-kuni-2/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 08 Apr 2018 13:39:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I was longing for something to smash my spare time on when I saw one of my favourite youtubers playing an interesting new video game. I was sold immediately. It’s called &lt;em&gt;Ni no Kuni 2: Revenant Kingdom&lt;/em&gt;. Interesting name aside, the game’s “art director” is none other than Studio Ghibli, and it shows. Fans of Ghibli’s films recognize the art style immediately. The score is also composed by Ghibli-regular Joe Hisaishi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I never played the previous game as I didn’t have the right consoles, so I was quite excited to learn that this one was available on Steam. I shelled out the salty 60€ for the game and set out on an adventure that would end up lasting for over 40 hours and giving me a lot of food for thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I’m about to explore is basically this: if you were a Japanese &lt;em&gt;salaryman&lt;/em&gt; game designer and just took a snapshot of recent news and the apparent &lt;em&gt;zeitgeist&lt;/em&gt;, what kind of world would you think we lived in? What kind of fairy tale would you tell? What would Walt Disney do? What kind of morals would you expect them to teach your children?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sequel’s market was shifted further towards a western audience, but stayed in a sweet spot reserved for an audience aware of “anime” and “ghibli”. Typically Japanese action role-playing games just do their Japan-crazy as usual and the west just learns to like some particular game due to the stars being aligned for once. But this time, they did their market research a bit… well, we’ll see. Let’s put it this way: the world is much more scarier on paper compared to living in it. Try reading the news for a while and pretend you’re reading the news of a distant country. Your local news become immediately so asinine you wouldn’t believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I embark on my adventure of curious observations, needless to say this post will &lt;strong&gt;SPOIL the entire story of the game&lt;/strong&gt;. If you’re not into action-adventure role-playing games, read on and enjoy a hearty guffaw. But if there’s a chance that you, dear reader, might enjoy the game, google it up first and see if makes you feel fuzzy inside (and have 40 hours to spend). If so, buy it and enjoy it with a pair of blue eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;inline-image&gt;
    
  &lt;a class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot; href=&quot;/static/20180408002129_1-4376da1b1fa563e264da91aaf9e20d0d-d7861.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display: block&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;
  
  &lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot; style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; ; max-width: 655px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot; style=&quot;padding-bottom: 56.26009693053311%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%; height: 100%; margin: 0; vertical-align: middle; position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; box-shadow: inset 0px 0px 0px 400px white;&quot; alt=&quot;20180408002129 1&quot; title=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/static/20180408002129_1-4376da1b1fa563e264da91aaf9e20d0d-163a3.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/static/20180408002129_1-4376da1b1fa563e264da91aaf9e20d0d-289e7.jpg 164w,
/static/20180408002129_1-4376da1b1fa563e264da91aaf9e20d0d-1d1f3.jpg 328w,
/static/20180408002129_1-4376da1b1fa563e264da91aaf9e20d0d-163a3.jpg 655w,
/static/20180408002129_1-4376da1b1fa563e264da91aaf9e20d0d-b92ec.jpg 983w,
/static/20180408002129_1-4376da1b1fa563e264da91aaf9e20d0d-14327.jpg 1310w,
/static/20180408002129_1-4376da1b1fa563e264da91aaf9e20d0d-11965.jpg 1965w,
/static/20180408002129_1-4376da1b1fa563e264da91aaf9e20d0d-d7861.jpg 2476w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 655px) 100vw, 655px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;
  
  &lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Genocide, am I right?!!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/inline-image&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It’s pre-emptive self-defense, not murder&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phrase &lt;em&gt;ni no kuni&lt;/em&gt; means literally “another world” and unsurprisingly proposes a very ghibliesque setting: there is the real world and a magical world alongside it. A protagonist gets sucked into this magic edition and shenanigans happen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game’s designers said in an interview that this time around they wanted to introduce an older character to attract a slightly more mature audience. That’s pretty easy, considering the previous games’ characters were mostly about 6 years old. The older character they introduced is Roland. Roland was the president of a country in the real world. The main protagonist is not Roland however, but Evan, a half-&lt;strong&gt;cat&lt;/strong&gt; boy-king, of all things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game begins and immediately things turn sour. The main antagonist Mausinger – the king’s advisor – is introduced. Mausinger stages a coup and a lot of people get killed. Evan needs to stop boohoo-ing that all his friends are dead to create a new kingdom where everyone can live &lt;em&gt;happily ever after&lt;/em&gt;. Roland the experienced statesman to the rescue! The game hasn’t even properly begun when the player is introduced to the theme of the game: the prime evil, racism. For some reason, most of the world’s nations’ leaders have been infected by an evil force which causes their behavior to change, typically towards hatefulness and selfishness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;inline-image&gt;
    
  &lt;a class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot; href=&quot;/static/rats-2c397fc6a3802636e07502cc6daa68d1-f9f6c.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display: block&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;
  
  &lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot; style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; ; max-width: 655px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot; style=&quot;padding-bottom: 57.38758029978587%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%; height: 100%; margin: 0; vertical-align: middle; position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; box-shadow: inset 0px 0px 0px 400px white;&quot; alt=&quot;rats&quot; title=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/static/rats-2c397fc6a3802636e07502cc6daa68d1-163a3.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/static/rats-2c397fc6a3802636e07502cc6daa68d1-289e7.jpg 164w,
/static/rats-2c397fc6a3802636e07502cc6daa68d1-1d1f3.jpg 328w,
/static/rats-2c397fc6a3802636e07502cc6daa68d1-163a3.jpg 655w,
/static/rats-2c397fc6a3802636e07502cc6daa68d1-b92ec.jpg 983w,
/static/rats-2c397fc6a3802636e07502cc6daa68d1-14327.jpg 1310w,
/static/rats-2c397fc6a3802636e07502cc6daa68d1-f9f6c.jpg 1401w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 655px) 100vw, 655px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;
  
  &lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Who let you out of the gulag?&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/inline-image&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t very uncommon, though. Throughout history a lot of fairy tales, Disney films and others have had a similar theme: social classes and races of citizens were portrayed by various animal species and the species were clearly animated in such a way that it was obvious who the good and bad guys were. What &lt;strong&gt;was&lt;/strong&gt; surprising how direct the game was with the subject. The way it was presented felt very… topical. The message was pretty clear: in spite of Evan’s moronic optimism, weak self-help quotes like &lt;em&gt;“justice always prevails”&lt;/em&gt; are false, and violence dictates the destiny of Ni no Kuni, just as it does in the real world. Roland and Evan must learn to swing a sword and the &lt;em&gt;action role-playing game&lt;/em&gt; genre has once again justified itself. Let’s go!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The lunacy of religion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Searching for answers and allies, Evan and Roland eventually arrive at the superstitious nation of Goldpaw, the country of the dogfolk. The dogs are completely insane: any state affair must involve a divine intervention. The dogs have a divine statue which is able to roll a die. The roll of the divine die decides everything from tax rates to criminal court hearings. All the dogs are in on it and believe fully in the justice of the die. Questioning the sanity of the divine die makes the dogs suspicious of the open-minded young king’s adventurous troupe. Sound familiar?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;inline-image&gt;
    
  &lt;a class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot; href=&quot;/static/funluck-1d8249cf10a8d556208e15d3eafcfa11-4ce49.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display: block&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;
  
  &lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot; style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; ; max-width: 655px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot; style=&quot;padding-bottom: 58.72291904218928%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%; height: 100%; margin: 0; vertical-align: middle; position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; box-shadow: inset 0px 0px 0px 400px white;&quot; alt=&quot;funluck&quot; title=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/static/funluck-1d8249cf10a8d556208e15d3eafcfa11-163a3.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/static/funluck-1d8249cf10a8d556208e15d3eafcfa11-289e7.jpg 164w,
/static/funluck-1d8249cf10a8d556208e15d3eafcfa11-1d1f3.jpg 328w,
/static/funluck-1d8249cf10a8d556208e15d3eafcfa11-163a3.jpg 655w,
/static/funluck-1d8249cf10a8d556208e15d3eafcfa11-4ce49.jpg 877w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 655px) 100vw, 655px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;
  
  &lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Outsourcing responsibility to imaginary things! Never heard that before.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/inline-image&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It gets better: the dogs have a charismatic leader, obviously! A priest-like ugly pug who presents himself as a humble servant of the dice roll. It’s obvious to the player that it’s just a mechanism to control the sheep, but the leader, as it turns out, wasn’t entirely to blame here. He was forced into it, like a cornered politician. Pretty meta! The dogs built giant factories which manufacture fake dice with built-in mechanisms for the country’s casinos and offices to manipulate everything. Again, a quite scoobydooesque plot but something in its design stamped a giant Cheshire grin on my face. I was liking the game immensely. God bless our freedom to believe what we choose to believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evan and pals rid Goldpaw of this cancer and suddenly many of the citizens gain a shed of rationality, especially after expressing their interest in joining Evan’s new kingdom of totally no internal issues. Immigration offices of the world: take note!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Leafbook&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was such a great feature I’m frankly quite stunned why stuff like this doesn’t play a part in games and films more often. Social media is not a phenomenon anymore – it’s a normal part of our daily lives. I think the lack of social media in entertainment in general is partly due to its non-ambiguity: social media is tied to a product or brand, such as Facebook or Twitter. In order to use social media, you have to call it by name. Using an existing product would make you endorse it. Coming up with a new one would cause the audience not to recognize it. Cities: Skylines, the Simcity-done-right, had its Chirper. Chirper’s purpose was to send “tweets” to the player to inform the player of citizens’ daily woes and other topical things. It worked fantastically, although eventually the tweets started to repeat themselves as they were just hard coded messages based on triggered events. Machine learning experts: the video game industry needs you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;inline-image&gt;
    
  &lt;a class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot; href=&quot;/static/leafbook-84bd0a5fdda7374e51411941282952e5-1228e.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display: block&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;
  
  &lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot; style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; ; max-width: 655px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot; style=&quot;padding-bottom: 55.052264808362374%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%; height: 100%; margin: 0; vertical-align: middle; position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; box-shadow: inset 0px 0px 0px 400px white;&quot; alt=&quot;leafbook&quot; title=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/static/leafbook-84bd0a5fdda7374e51411941282952e5-163a3.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/static/leafbook-84bd0a5fdda7374e51411941282952e5-289e7.jpg 164w,
/static/leafbook-84bd0a5fdda7374e51411941282952e5-1d1f3.jpg 328w,
/static/leafbook-84bd0a5fdda7374e51411941282952e5-163a3.jpg 655w,
/static/leafbook-84bd0a5fdda7374e51411941282952e5-b92ec.jpg 983w,
/static/leafbook-84bd0a5fdda7374e51411941282952e5-1228e.jpg 1148w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 655px) 100vw, 655px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;
  
  &lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Check out these selfies bruh.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/inline-image&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ni no Kuni 2 has Leafbook – an amalgamation of Facebook and Twitter where every post is an image with a caption. New posts appear systematically as the player progresses through the story. Non-player characters the player might have already met also comment on the images, gossiping and providing other details. The player is not able to post anything, but browsing posts gives the player hints on possible secrets and characters to recruit to Evan’s kingdom. It’s fairly passive and completely unnecessary for beating the game, but it’s a fun and intuitive detail and offers treasure hunting players extra activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Worship or suffer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next stop on our adventure to societal failures is ideologically a bit further away but alive and well nonetheless. Turns out the fish people, merfolk, are ruled by fear. Fleeing their country is really difficult, outsiders are greeted by a military escort and the tyrant queen has decreed a bunch of ridiculous laws known as the Four Pillars. The Four Pillars forbid some obvious things, such as being sick and falling in love. The queen herself is a bit of a recluse – she hasn’t shown herself to her subjects in years. This would have a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; strong smell of classic Disney if it weren’t for the queen herself, who happens to be a bit of a “lick my foot” type of dominating weirdo. The loved queen isn’t even merfolk, but human! I’m pretty sure I’ve heard of this place before, but I can’t quite put my finger on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;inline-image&gt;
    
  &lt;a class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot; href=&quot;/static/forbiddenlove-681f539d0b5f531efa066dec91077d4a-1280b.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display: block&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;
  
  &lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot; style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; ; max-width: 655px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot; style=&quot;padding-bottom: 49.644549763033176%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%; height: 100%; margin: 0; vertical-align: middle; position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; box-shadow: inset 0px 0px 0px 400px white;&quot; alt=&quot;forbiddenlove&quot; title=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/static/forbiddenlove-681f539d0b5f531efa066dec91077d4a-163a3.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/static/forbiddenlove-681f539d0b5f531efa066dec91077d4a-289e7.jpg 164w,
/static/forbiddenlove-681f539d0b5f531efa066dec91077d4a-1d1f3.jpg 328w,
/static/forbiddenlove-681f539d0b5f531efa066dec91077d4a-163a3.jpg 655w,
/static/forbiddenlove-681f539d0b5f531efa066dec91077d4a-1280b.jpg 844w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 655px) 100vw, 655px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;
  
  &lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Zora in Breath of the Wild had more fashion sense than these guys.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/inline-image&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The locals are fairly primitive and live in large ruined ancient Greek type of rickety structures and their ruler expresses her love in a quite indirect, inconspicuous way by observing the actions of citizens with a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; eyeball tower (think Sauron’s eye) which is able to detect every single action you make. Pleasant. Plot twist: in the end it was just the queen making sure the country is safe, because reasons. Again Evan &amp;#x26; co save the day and a bunch of people want to move over to his country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Technommunism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Broadleaf, the makers of our Leafbook, is a nation focused on improving the world with magic-based technology. There is no royalty here – in a super-orwellian fashion the entire nation is one single company and the CEO acts as the president. As you’d expect, the CEO is under an influence and people are dying. All that matters is the completion of the latest product. Upon entering the city, Evan and friends are greeted with a workers strike. A proper rally with engineers and scientists yelling catchy war cries and waving edgy signs. People are dying in factories when workers’ physical and mental health don’t matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time violence isn’t enough to save the day. In addition to violence we need memories and compassion to banish the greed. If only the real world had lobbyists trying to install some kind of conscience to shareholders’ heads. Maybe underpaid slave-like workers in countries with questionable morals could just slay some executives with a sword and be celebrated afterwards. It might work just as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Building the wall&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a lot of weird encounters with the citizens of the world, it’s time to go home – the old home where Mausinger now reigns. The kingdom was previously a kingdom of the grimalkin, cat-like humanoids. Now it’s a kingdom for mice and rats, who in the beginning of the game were presented as the bad guys. Many grimalkin escaped but the ones who remain are treated as trash, guards punch them for sport and people spit on them. But then… shit starts to get real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evan and friends walk around town trying to learn the whereabouts of the grimalkin. Turns out they’ve been driven to the sewers, like unwanted immigrants. In disguise Evan talks to citizens of this new nation and learns the cold truth: &lt;em&gt;his old kingdom was an apartheid&lt;/em&gt;, and he as the sheltered prince wasn’t told about it. The mice are &lt;em&gt;free&lt;/em&gt; from centuries of oppression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;inline-image&gt;
    
  &lt;a class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot; href=&quot;/static/20180407175613_1-09b1128de8d683bd570b5791660611ef-d7861.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display: block&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;
  
  &lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot; style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; ; max-width: 655px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot; style=&quot;padding-bottom: 56.26009693053311%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%; height: 100%; margin: 0; vertical-align: middle; position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; box-shadow: inset 0px 0px 0px 400px white;&quot; alt=&quot;20180407175613 1&quot; title=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/static/20180407175613_1-09b1128de8d683bd570b5791660611ef-163a3.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/static/20180407175613_1-09b1128de8d683bd570b5791660611ef-289e7.jpg 164w,
/static/20180407175613_1-09b1128de8d683bd570b5791660611ef-1d1f3.jpg 328w,
/static/20180407175613_1-09b1128de8d683bd570b5791660611ef-163a3.jpg 655w,
/static/20180407175613_1-09b1128de8d683bd570b5791660611ef-b92ec.jpg 983w,
/static/20180407175613_1-09b1128de8d683bd570b5791660611ef-14327.jpg 1310w,
/static/20180407175613_1-09b1128de8d683bd570b5791660611ef-11965.jpg 1965w,
/static/20180407175613_1-09b1128de8d683bd570b5791660611ef-d7861.jpg 2476w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 655px) 100vw, 655px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;
  
  &lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Lesson in politics: our happiness is not your happiness.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/inline-image&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mice are happy! They are happy that they feel empowered. They are happy that they have a common enemy which they just recently beat. They revel in the intoxicating feeling of superiority… except the ones who were servants and allies of the murdered court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evan learns what it takes to make citizens happy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Come up with enemies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publicly display your strength to your citizens&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Empower your own citizens with weapons, status or money&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anybody order a needless missile strike lately?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evan had himself been doing these things all the time along the way, not quite understanding what it meant. I would have loved to hear Roland’s comments on the state of things, him being an actual president and all. Oh, and one thing I forgot to mention: in the first 15 seconds of the game, in the game’s opening cutscene, Roland’s home country is destroyed in a nuclear strike. Let’s fucking go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;inline-image&gt;
    
  &lt;a class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot; href=&quot;/static/20180407175555_1-5f80d4393cc986f368a12218b8fdf4b4-d7861.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display: block&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;
  
  &lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot; style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; ; max-width: 655px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot; style=&quot;padding-bottom: 56.26009693053311%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%; height: 100%; margin: 0; vertical-align: middle; position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; box-shadow: inset 0px 0px 0px 400px white;&quot; alt=&quot;20180407175555 1&quot; title=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/static/20180407175555_1-5f80d4393cc986f368a12218b8fdf4b4-163a3.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/static/20180407175555_1-5f80d4393cc986f368a12218b8fdf4b4-289e7.jpg 164w,
/static/20180407175555_1-5f80d4393cc986f368a12218b8fdf4b4-1d1f3.jpg 328w,
/static/20180407175555_1-5f80d4393cc986f368a12218b8fdf4b4-163a3.jpg 655w,
/static/20180407175555_1-5f80d4393cc986f368a12218b8fdf4b4-b92ec.jpg 983w,
/static/20180407175555_1-5f80d4393cc986f368a12218b8fdf4b4-14327.jpg 1310w,
/static/20180407175555_1-5f80d4393cc986f368a12218b8fdf4b4-11965.jpg 1965w,
/static/20180407175555_1-5f80d4393cc986f368a12218b8fdf4b4-d7861.jpg 2476w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 655px) 100vw, 655px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;
  
  &lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;I think the question was: &amp;quot;Could I make the kingdom great again?&amp;quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/inline-image&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;I lied&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you read this and &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; played the game, you’re probably wondering what the hell am I raving on about. These are really the main events of the story, excluding the final chapters. However, I left a critical piece out: what was it that caused the world’s nations to go crazy like they did? This little detail kind of undoes most of what I just told. That detail is irrelevant, but it acts as a reality check. I remember as a child these stories were everywhere: something bad happens but then its always undone by cringy bullshit which would &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; happen in real life, so why were these stories told? To raise stupider citizens? Without this unnamed cartoony antagonist the game would basically be a horror game. If it wasn’t for this little detail, the shiny-ass Ghibli art style, and the protagonists’ sanity-defying naive optimism, most of the game’s script could just as well be written by Nietzsche.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if! What if our world is plagued by a similar insanity and it can all be cured with a simple concept, but no one has ever come across it. There’s a malicious power keeping us from achieving peace. Roland had his ride so help us out, Evan. Maybe it’s your turn to hop over to our side and rustle a jimmy. Wake us up from this world of distasteful, untrustworthy and egotistic people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think? If our world could change one thing which would fix everything, what would it be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;inline-image&gt;
    
  &lt;a class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot; href=&quot;/static/20180407175345_1-dbf8f37160ff7f05f14bb2a33178aff7-d7861.jpg&quot; style=&quot;display: block&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;
  
  &lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot; style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; ; max-width: 655px; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot; style=&quot;padding-bottom: 56.26009693053311%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%; height: 100%; margin: 0; vertical-align: middle; position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; box-shadow: inset 0px 0px 0px 400px white;&quot; alt=&quot;20180407175345 1&quot; title=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/static/20180407175345_1-dbf8f37160ff7f05f14bb2a33178aff7-163a3.jpg&quot; srcset=&quot;/static/20180407175345_1-dbf8f37160ff7f05f14bb2a33178aff7-289e7.jpg 164w,
/static/20180407175345_1-dbf8f37160ff7f05f14bb2a33178aff7-1d1f3.jpg 328w,
/static/20180407175345_1-dbf8f37160ff7f05f14bb2a33178aff7-163a3.jpg 655w,
/static/20180407175345_1-dbf8f37160ff7f05f14bb2a33178aff7-b92ec.jpg 983w,
/static/20180407175345_1-dbf8f37160ff7f05f14bb2a33178aff7-14327.jpg 1310w,
/static/20180407175345_1-dbf8f37160ff7f05f14bb2a33178aff7-11965.jpg 1965w,
/static/20180407175345_1-dbf8f37160ff7f05f14bb2a33178aff7-d7861.jpg 2476w&quot; sizes=&quot;(max-width: 655px) 100vw, 655px&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;
  
  &lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Are you sure? We have a lot of leaders in here Roland&amp;apos;s world who could take that advice &amp;#x2013; politics aside.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/inline-image&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Evaluating life]]></title><description><![CDATA[Notice/update: this post was written under extreme mental stress and is not to be taken seriously. I’m leaving it as a reminder for how…]]></description><link>http://rapuhotelli.net/2018/evaluation/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://rapuhotelli.net/2018/evaluation/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2018 13:39:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice/update: this post was written under extreme mental stress and is not to be taken seriously. I’m leaving it as a reminder for how easily things can get sour if you don’t take care of yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workplace switch, 2 months later. It went pretty much exactly as I expected (or feared) it would. I enjoy the company of my colleagues and I feel good whenever I’m able to deliver a meaningful contribution. I spend a considerable amount of time at the office because I have nothing else on my mind. However, what I &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/enter-2018/&quot;&gt;previously feared&lt;/a&gt; came to pass. What I thought was the top of the world was in actuality just a world for people whose minds have remained unshattered. Part of me wishes I had remained behind in my old daily routine where I was safe, and part of me wants to see opportunities in this – opportunities for a distant salvation. But the truth is I am tired. I have grown weary of the constant struggle between me and the world I perceive as unfair, even when I know everything is more or less fine. It’s all about the &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/meaning-of-life&quot;&gt;demand&lt;/a&gt;, and I my ability to resist is fading. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again I scared myself the past weekend when a person said something I wish they hadn’t said. I was reminded of the gleeful innocence many people are able to live in, delivered like a slap in the face. “I didn’t know people could &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; just be lonely”, was said. I wish I never had to learn either. Imagine being so privileged that you can choose not to ever be socially responsible for your behavior. Imagine being so privileged that you can ignore people around you if they do not entertain you. Imagine being so privileged that you can not actually know what loneliness is. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My madness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprise! It was high time for my annual anxiety attack. I felt a familiar, bitter rage boil inside me that could only be described as madness. I see thought-clouding red everywhere, but it’s not anger, exactly. My madness is disbelief mixed with bitter amusement. Imagine a Disney villain laughing maniacally. It’s an utter, surreal disappointment in the world. Of course, I bear no ill will toward any of the human beings I encounter. Rather, I see people as vessels sent to &lt;strong&gt;laugh at me&lt;/strong&gt; at my expense like schoolyard bullies – except the bullies are everyone in the world. &lt;em&gt;Never forget that&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;have failed. You do not belong among us&lt;/em&gt;, they scream, blaming for something I cannot grasp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, my madness is a coping mechanism of a kind. For the majority of my childhood I had to believe everyone were evil and hunted me, transforming me into a silent, scared recluse and giving me my only sense of safety. It never quite went away, I guess. Little triggers related to injustice and intentional harm brings it out and the best way to fight against it is to minimize risks when dealing with people I don’t know so well. Unsurprisingly, this is the reason I left politics and volunteer work. I don’t need to be convinced if (or when) the world is going to burn. I already know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And just like that… it was over. I’m proud of myself that this time it didn’t last that long. Typically I suppress emotions gone wild by eating so much I pass out, to prevent further harm, but this time my madness lasted only an hour or two. I took this opportunity to contemplate and decided I should probably come up with some kind of goals for life. I believe this “depression” of mine is curable if I ever became satisfied with myself, that is, not carrying the blaming weight of the world on my shoulders. So, having something to &lt;em&gt;go for&lt;/em&gt; might help with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New purposes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve arranged my life in such way that I may enjoy a “groundhog day” for as long as I’m able to maintain it. This is why a change of employer is such a big deal for me. In a groundhog day, I am safe. It’s predictable. Breaking it would expose me to the world, which is probably what I need the most, really… Being vulnerable without fear. I identify the following things as my key obstacles and changing them somehow would help the most, but I’m having a hard time affecting them in my current groundhog state. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Professional identity&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professionally I should pick a focus. I hail from the early days of the internet where specializations didn’t exist, and today not specializing is a slow, stressful suicide. However, my new employer (which I love to death) encourages generalization, further adding to my stress. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Home function&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now my home is worthless. It’s just a place where I sleep and spend some time so that the next workday came around sooner. I try to do “hobbies” at home, like music and cooking and whatever, but it’s shallow. I don’t get true satisfaction from my time at home. Is that normal? How would I improve this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Love somebody&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is something I try not to think of. This is the greatest exposure of your weaknesses and I’m probably never going to be able to risk it again. Then again, it offers the greatest risk-reward ratio regarding sanity, but the rational nerd in me tosses this aside as a completely irrelevant task – there simply isn’t &lt;em&gt;enough&lt;/em&gt; to be gained. The &lt;em&gt;non&lt;/em&gt;-rational human being is also suspicious: as time passes I find it increasingly harder to express any kind of realistic infatuation. I don’t have the energy to go after a partner, and as a quote on one of our office’s whiteboards elegantly put it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Love is like a fart. If you have to force it, it’s probably shit.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Love anybody&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean, I have friends and I love them but true friends… not very many. Whenever I’m in danger of befriending someone too closely, I usually strayed away in an effort to maintain a safe distance. People most often acted strangely and I felt some awkward expectations. Counter-intuitively, this is probably the easiest one to fix. I have people around me – I just need to trust them more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Next&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There. Some thoughts. I’m going to start with professional identity first as it’s something I don’t need a third party to improve. Being happier at work is such a huge deal for me and it would easily radiate into the other topics. I know what I want to do professionally, but I’ve just had really bad luck regarding actual real world opportunities to do it. Even writing this down further strengthens my resolve.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Health check]]></title><description><![CDATA[So… a new job, huh?  It’s weird, though. I don’t know where I’m going. Why even change company and take a colossal financial risk (not to…]]></description><link>http://rapuhotelli.net/2018/health/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://rapuhotelli.net/2018/health/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2018 16:25:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So… a new job, huh?&lt;/em&gt; It’s weird, though. I don’t know where I’m going. Why even change company and take a colossal financial risk (not to mention risking sanity), if everything was fine? Overcoming the fear of new challenges and doing all of the social workout bullshit all over again with an even larger group of people. Why would you do that? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I managed to nearly completely reset my social circles, for starters. For some reason I fought against it a little, but I have finally become a victim of my field – the greatest people I know are professionals, and the more time I spend with them the more the world seems to be at peace. When people say you marry your work, I guess this is what they mean - including the nagging feeling of dread, the disappointments, and hoping that the inevitable divorce would come on your terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ban all the things!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, a fairly refreshing change of pace. So refreshing that I decided to basically kill myself ;) No, not literally (let’s wait for it), but efficiently and swiftly detaching myself from many of the old vices that so well defined me in a life gone by. It feels like plucking feathers off of a fat pigeon until what remains is a dysfunctional blob and looks even dumber than before. &lt;em&gt;*Cough*…&lt;/em&gt; more specifically, I’m starting with a complete ban on coffee and nicotine, cold turkey style!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did mean coffee and not caffeine. I react very strongly to coffee for some reason. Most energy drinks are fine, though the overdose of sugar is an entirely different story. So far three weeks without coffee feels pretty great: I sleep well, I am not tired at work and I can actually focus at work. I do miss the &lt;em&gt;habit&lt;/em&gt; - having an excuse to wander about and initiating conversations. I outsourced my motivation to my colleagues. If they see me with coffee, they are obligated to slap me in the face or perform any other unspecified violation. It’s a great motivator!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Nicodemus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real fight here is nicotine. I did quit active smoking a while back, because the state of my lungs does interest me, but the &lt;em&gt;snus&lt;/em&gt; used up here in the north is just so pleasant, harmless and a fun little hobby, albeit sometimes smelly. It’s the little fact that deep inside I don’t actually want to quit nicotine. It sounds dumb but I really owe nicotine a large chunk of my sanity, success and friends. A cigarette was my little, miserable candle in the dark. A cigarette was one of the only moral choices I could make myself in an utterly defeated mindset. If I wanted to smoke a cigarette I would fucking smoke it and I would receive that tiny little rebellious satisfaction from it. I don’t regret a single cigarette I’ve had even if tomorrow I collapsed from a mystery cancer. It’s easy to be smug about a statement like that but you have to understand the utter defeat people can face and the scale of the smallest of joys. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, I don’t particularly &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; nicotine anymore. The hill I’ve climbed is quite the queen of all nipples but I can do without, for now. Nicotine in one form or another was closely associated with my friends, who later took a different path in life and I rarely see them anymore nor would I care to. The actual struggle is filling that hobby with something else &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; the help of nicotine. Every day I get this feeling that &lt;em&gt;oh this installs for 30 minutes? what a good time for a smoke&lt;/em&gt;. What do people normally do? Even without nicotine I am restless and I must focus on some distraction at all times to prevent me from actually getting distracted. I allow myself downtime only if I’m able to justify it - with a smoke, for example. Is this what the fidget spinner craze was about? Is this what people do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mission is to keep my head straight. For the longest time I didn’t want to even think of quitting just for the sake of my friends. Withdrawal gives me strange anxiety problems and wildly swinging moods. I get grumpy very easily and the simplest things irritate me. Recovering from these grumpiness sessions is quite fascinating, actually. They’re followed by intense periods of self-consciousness where I brutally judge myself and distance myself from my friends who totally don’t “deserve me” or something equally dramatic. It’s a slippery slope I have to monitor very closely, as the mental drop can deal a large amount of damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Old vices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not that bad now, though. It’s not like I have many close friends anymore and right now all I really care about is my work, and the only thing I should really be worrying about is upsetting my clients. That’s a stretch. You could argue social ineptitude caused by nicotine withdrawal &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be factored into professional competence pretty easily, but in a month or two it has all but breezed through. Fingers crossed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isn’t it weird to sound so rational about quitting something like nicotine? It’s not even a properly psychoactive drug! Well, it’s just that I’ve done this before. My first milestone is one month without nicotine, after which I’m clean. Now, as I write this I’m thinking to myself: what for? Why? I’m sure my co-workers would appreciate me being nicotine-free but what do I gain? Can my co-workers fill in the happiness it gave me all these years? Nicotine leaves a huge hole in my soul - especially in the Stress Management Department. It must be filled and I don’t know how. There’s a risk it just comes back and next time I might not bother pretending if it’s for better or worse.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Enter 2018 - the dream for nothing]]></title><description><![CDATA[2017 turned out to be nearly worthless. I spoke with a bunch of friends and strangely many of them agree. In 2017 almost nothing happened…]]></description><link>http://rapuhotelli.net/2018/enter-2018/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://rapuhotelli.net/2018/enter-2018/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2018 17:31:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;2017 turned out to be nearly worthless. I spoke with a bunch of friends and strangely many of them agree. In 2017 almost nothing happened, nothing in life or work seemed to progress and most of the year was spent in pubs with friends, drowning away confused thoughts. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did reach a considerable milestone, though. I applied for a job I had dreamed of for a long time and I kinda regret I didn’t do it sooner, but only &lt;em&gt;kinda&lt;/em&gt; regret. Your life is the sum of the choices you make – just remember to hold your head up high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They did accept me, much to my surprise. My application was the the most humble and nerdiest thing I have ever written (it still makes me laugh) but I stand by my words with all my nerdy heart. Employers who are not uptight whitecollars are rare. Yes, they are rare. Sometimes in the startup bubble you become blinded to what the world outside can be like. I consider myself very &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; lucky to work in my field, and even more luckier to have stumbled across employers of such greatness, even if work… is what it is sometimes. I am somewhat socially awkward and generally weird at life and I couldn’t imagine doing anything else. It’s truly a privilege. Time will tell how long it’ll last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Weirding it out&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one not-very-small detail though: having reached this point, I no longer have anything to dream about. I have reached all of my far-fetched milestones I laid out for me some 15 years ago. I am mortified. What if my depression comes back? If you’re unaware how depression works, just google up some webcomic strips about it ;) In my case the trigger is the feeling of inadequacy in contrast to the people around me. In practice this is a Catch-22. It’s stupid, but I cannot see value in myself. I just want to contribute and see people happy. When I had my farewell party at the previous company, my co-workers gave me epic parting gifts. I had no idea how to thank them. I just mumbled something. Later at home I was so weirded out by it all. “Focus on your own things, fools”. I couldn’t look at the mirror - usually I was the one planning things to make other peoples’ heads spin. Why can’t I be on the other side?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, in a new working environment I’m afraid I might come to view the others as my betters, not as my peers. This would eventually spiral into self-disrespect fueled by the achievements of others and eliminate my drive to be that happy and enthusastic organizer guy. I would view it as a bitter charity. This is the thing: pretty much the only thing I truly enjoy is my work. I am unable to take on long, serious relationships and thus I &lt;em&gt;pray&lt;/em&gt; to whoever deity cares to listen that I befriend my colleagues well enough to sustain my social needs, and that the friendships are true and involve no jealousy on my part for those whose lives haven’t been as …eventful as mine. I still have room to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Exhaustion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October I decided it’s now or never. I had to send that application now or I’ll be stuck. I felt a Stockholm syndrome whispering to me. Considering how personal my application was, you can imagine how exhausting it was when the process took its time. I literally bought a FitBit wristband to inspect my heart rate during the interviews. At work I got concerned comments that I looked like I’d seen a ghost. I think I might just have. The time from sending the application to writing the contract took two months almost to the day, and even then I didn’t have the heart to start as soon as possible as I’d leave my current work in a pinch. So overall the process took 3.5 months. Considering how seriously I take the job you can imagine my despair. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I write this, I’m only a weekend away. I’m taking this opportunity to forcibly introduce a lot of changes into my life at the same time. I’ve noticed many changes at once are easier than incremental changes. I’m planning to lose some weight, for instance. I’m planning to live a lot more healthily. Eliminate alcohol as much as I socially can. I’m planning to see my friends and play board games or whatever - not being drunk. I’m planning on doing hobbyist things, such as music and games, to keep myself entertained. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time will tell! I just hope everything will be alright and I no longer have to drown my thoughts into a pint of relief. There has always been light at the end of the tunnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS. A year ago I spoke of a lack of identity. It’s not healed but it has become more… intangible. I can relate to some people!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[So, you're a Full-Stack Developer]]></title><description><![CDATA[Every time someone says they are a “full-stack developer” I feel a sharp, nostalgic jolt up my spine. You might be one, but most likely you…]]></description><link>http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/full-stack/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/full-stack/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2017 16:20:13 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Every time someone says they are a “full-stack developer” I feel a sharp, nostalgic jolt up my spine. You might be one, but most likely you are not. Or, like me, at some point in time you were.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, a “full-stack developer” is a term used to describe someone who has the skillset to develop and deploy a product all on their own. For my kind of furious nerds who read every possible tech blog in a desperate attempt to understand what’s going on in the development world, being a full-stack is the ultimate goal. It means you are invincible. Today, however, it’s just too much. You have to focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in as recently as about 2010 (or so) being full-stack was relatively easy. The golden age of server-rendered MVC applications had just reached its peak. I got into Linux servers to study Apache and Nginx just get the satisfaction from the knowledge of being able to do it. Full-Stack back then was in essence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose our favorite MVC framework. Make some fancy-ass models, controllers and views. Extend a bunch of classes to be cool as fuck.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be proficient in SQL.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do some CSS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have access to a server which you can configure yourself to run your app.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you wanted actual scaling due to large amount of page views you needed special skills that were beyond full-stack. If you had to scale &lt;em&gt;shit got real&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you were poor you could have a server under your bed which runs your app (along with irssi and your torrents or whatever).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used PHP frameworks mostly and the choices were abundant. Early on I used something called CakePHP a lot, which &lt;a href=&quot;https://cakephp.org/&quot;&gt;still seems to be kicking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my studies I had a friend who had made his own &lt;a href=&quot;https://jonikorpi.com/less-framework/&quot;&gt;CSS grid “framework”&lt;/a&gt;. It was ace and I quite liked it. Sensible CSS toolkits didn’t really exist and the concept of bringing large-scale sanity into stylesheets had just barely been invented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hardest part was the server. The whole world of hosting was obscure as all hell, as it was really hard to find “tutorials” in a very academic unix world. Documentation existed, but applying that information to your needs was another beast entirely. You needed friends to show you the ropes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, we have the cloud. And not just the cloud, but today applications are far more complex. In my personal opinion, they are far more complex than is necessary. It’s a trap the industry has dug itself into, but that is a story for another time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting up a “full”, safe, and scaling web app is so much work that it’s very impractical to do on your own. The risk of misconfiguration is very high, especially in the cloud. Today, instead of being able to git clone an MVP and call it a day, &lt;em&gt;full-stack is a set of skills that theoretically enable joining a project in any part of the project.&lt;/em&gt; However, the details of that project are not necessarily yours to define, so it’s likely that your Full-Stack Developer would still lack a necessary skill. It all comes down to the near hysterical complexity of internet today. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s your typical considerations in 2017:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose your language and platform based on a bunch of conditions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the end result of the app? What are the performance requirements for page load speed and server capacity and how does it scale? Does it have to scale?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are your mobile considerations: make a separate mobile app or just “mobile first”? How well can it survive without constant supervision? Could you do that mobile app as well?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many people are going to be working on it and do they need to learn anything? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that the language and platform are chosen, decide on how your front-end should work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re doing client-side apps, what is the technology stack?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you prepared to start configuring webpack and Babel to get your anus destroyed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does your full-stackness involve UX competence or do you include &lt;em&gt;npm install bootstrap&lt;/em&gt; as a part of your expertise?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since you’re probably doing an API based app, we’re going to assume you daydream of OAuth specifications and GraphQL statements. Don’t forget to write your unit tests. We’re also assuming you know what database types to use and when.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re almost done. All you need now is to understand how the cloud actually works, and no, I don’t mean running an EC2 container with a bunch of dockerized things in it. In the traditional full-stack mindset you would also set up the pipes that build your cloudy container images for you with all the security groups and autoscales and all that. For me, this is the train stop where I get off. Maybe in the future I will handle this as well, but there is only a limited amount of hours in a day and I get my kicks from actual programming and product design. Sanity prevails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you notice that today we considered scaling and in the past we did not? That’s because how the application is developed and deployed is integral to how its scaling is going to work due to the inevitable continuous integration and continuous deployment setups which, ofcourse, are your job as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a reason why developers are in massive demand. There are so many possible end results and variations that no single person can do it &lt;em&gt;with confidence.&lt;/em&gt; All of the parts of modern web development have so much depth, and considering the historical context for the term “full-stack”, calling yourself full-stack in, say, job interviews should raise some flags. More than likely you don’t know what the word means or you’re trusting that your interviewer will gloss over the use of the term. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a weird topic to have strong opinions on, but I strongly believe you should just call yourself a “Web Developer” and then focus on your existing skillset and expanding your skillset. In fact, it’s rare that anyone involved with the web would focus on just one part of it. If you’re &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; confident about your experience, just use a Senior prefix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ofcourse, you’re free to defined the word as you see fit. Everyone does it, afterall. However, using the term properly is a good sign that you understand your profession and is considered &lt;em&gt;best practice&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The meaning of life, obviously]]></title><description><![CDATA[I asked a friend what should I write about next. “Talk about the meaning of life”, was the obvious answer. Let’s do it, then. Definition…]]></description><link>http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/meaning-of-life/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/meaning-of-life/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2017 17:32:39 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I asked a friend what should I write about next. “Talk about the meaning of life”, was the obvious answer. Let’s do it, then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Definition&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: this is in context of a westerner who lives in abundance as the question was asked by such a person. Different philosophical branches have a very different take on what is happiness and what is life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start with, life is not a toy you can buy so the question is not &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; is the meaning of life, but more like how to make life feel meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem of the meaning of life is quite easy to define, but associating yourself with the definition is the hard part. The approach I take is the approach of an utilitarian engineer. Go figure…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the whole picture:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are probably a human being, a pack animal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You were born without being asked if you wanted or not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of stuff happens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will eventually die &lt;em&gt;probably&lt;/em&gt; without being asked when would you like to die.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is forced onto you and at the end you will die. I keep reading lame quotes where someone on their deathbed laments that the one thing they regret is something-or-other, typically not taking some opportunities or not seeing the world or whatever. I think having any regrets like this, or forcibly doing things in fear of having similar deathbed regrets is completely against the purpose of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply put, the meaning of life is to live your life and enjoy the ride. Cheesy, yeah, but the hard part is to make people realize how should they enjoy it, or to be precise, what should they be satisfied in so that they can take pleasure in that satisfaction. The challenge depends on the individual in question, but typically you can just ask: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are you satisfied with your daily life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are not, why? What can you do about it? Why not?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, cheese, but let’s take a closer look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Demand&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average western person often sees their life as an empty shell. This is even more true today than ever before, now when internet dominates our social lives and social media completely saturates what we perceive of others and the society around us. I like to think that we have a &lt;em&gt;Demand&lt;/em&gt;, which is a constant. When you are a child you have a demand for simple things, but you feel very strongly about it. As you grow up, you still have demand but you learn to manage it. At some point you reach the point where your demand has only value in relation to the people around you. You have a job, hobbies, a spouse, friends, stuff. Still you demand but now what to demand is presented to you by your surroundings. Buy a car, gain status. Buy a house, gain status. Are you limited by money or other societal factors? You can always present yourself to others in such a way that you appear being something that the society would expect of you. Fear the stigma!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Demand makes you feel incomplete for the entirety of your life. Everywhere you look you see only things you desire - you learn to ignore the rest. I want to be that person! &lt;em&gt;He&lt;/em&gt; doesn’t appreciate what he has as much as I would, give it to me! I &lt;em&gt;demand&lt;/em&gt; a raise, I am worth more than this! For the majority of your life you are in a Demand state where the next step seems unreachable and you start asking these questions. What do I do with my life? How did I get into this mess? &lt;em&gt;What is the meaning of life?&lt;/em&gt; A person without Demand could be considered depressed and is “cured” once they able to reach for the next step again, demand just a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if something changes in your life and you fall down? It’s a shock. Something you depended on is no more and you are almost paralyzed and you cling on to the things you have, maybe reaching for support. Eventually you find a foothold in something and you feel stable again, but it’s far from where you left off. Still, you are satisfied, relieved. The world you came from seems distant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fall is often attributed to spiritual awakenings and other phenomena in which the person in question declares they now find meaning in their life - post-traumatically. I believe this is what everyone should look forward to. A similar effect drives all religions, politics and other movements. Recently only populism has started to move the average masses whose Demand is not movable by their own merit. Other movements just do not have the personal connection required to shake the Demand at its core.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are an average western person who has it all but lack meaning of life, you have several options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make a radical change in your life to force the Demand out of hiding. This could be anything. Move abroad. Sell everything you have. Someone feels the safety of the home is choking their Demand and choose a divorce. You decide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn not to Demand. Visualize the path that took you all the way up to this point and fucking be happy about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accept the existence of Demand and embrace it, just understand that it exists and don’t let it dominate your life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Bonus!) Make the society enforce the Demand upon you. Go to war. Do some crimes and go to jail. Vote for chaos in your next election, etc. Arrange the society so that your primal desires become justified instead of irresponsible. (Not recommended, but seems to be popular these days).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, getting back to regrets: I don’t think you should regret anything. Remember that you will die. You will just die. Dying of old age is not a better or “less regretful” death than dying sooner. The only way dying of old age is better is that there’s a higher chance of not having your friends around mourning for you anymore, but even then you’re no longer there to care. Being old, lonely and miserable sucks ass and everyone should avoid it. Ask any geriatrician. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just live your life and Demand things that you know are reachable in order to have a steady supply of meaningful satisfaction to you and to you only [1]. Not to be confused with selfishness. “You cannot love others until you learn to love yourself” is a classic cheese but very valid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] I’ll probably come back later to how you would manipulate the Demand to your own benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS.
For the entirety of my life I’ve wished upon a force majeure that would bless me with choice #1 but that is really hard to arrange yourself. I’m somewhere between #2 and #3 as I feel I got started on an average life about 10 years after people normally do but that, again, is a story for another time.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Development for what]]></title><description><![CDATA[I watched Ryan Dahl’s presentation on Node.js back then. A friend linked it to me and said it was gonna be big. I understood it was going to…]]></description><link>http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/for-what/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/for-what/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2017 15:45:31 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I watched Ryan Dahl’s presentation on Node.js back then. A friend linked it to me and said it was gonna be big. I understood it was going to be big, just not how big it would become. Every developer has their own take on this story and this is mine. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the 2000s web development was… different, but also much &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; simpler to learn. There was a lot of hype on Ruby, which campaigned against PHP as being more hip. MVC frameworks were cool as fuck. They are still cool to me. I like OOP quite much. I’m an engineer by heart and OOP is very easy to understand and develop. Ofcourse, these days I know that for larger projects with multiple developers OOP easily becomes a giant clusterfuck, but that is a story for another time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole development world and ecosystem were very academic - it was just programming. You always used the tools and libraries that were carefully crafted and stable. When it came to things that had the slightest risk of misusing something, it was always clearly emphasized how to not make an insecure thing. At best people linked to academic papers on input validation and even how to structure HTML properly in a best effort prevent browser parsing bugs or JavaScript bugs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frameworks did a lot of magic JavaScript. You used the framework’s own classes to render things on the page and it magically rendered all kinds of baked-in form validators and all kinds of things, so you wouldn’t have to. If you wanted to AJAX something yourself, that was &lt;em&gt;rad&lt;/em&gt;. You’d make an endpoint using your fancy-ass framework and it might render HTML directly and your jQuery or whatever would paste that HTML onto the page. Cool as fuck. Someone crazy might have used just JSON responses and jQueried something into the page and they would be asked: “Why would you do this? Just let the &lt;em&gt;application&lt;/em&gt; render what you wanted.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked with people who were front-end developers. That was new. You had people who on purpose did not do “backend”, but focused on colours, layout composition and even &lt;em&gt;typography&lt;/em&gt;. Some even did some JavaScript. I let them do their thing, but it was the first time I encountered an interesting (today very common) phenomenon: something that was designed to present itself in a specific way was not actually very easily doable by the MVC application. You lost the academic control of the application to something abstract and took risks regarding the functionality of the application in favor of &lt;em&gt;art&lt;/em&gt;. That was crazy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here’s the thing: the so-called front-end developers were not interested in the application as such. As time passed they did more and more JavaScript, which was great. jQuery and such were amazing. Once Node.js launched, people rejoiced. A new movement arose where using some special service you could easily “deploy an app” which was written in Node.js and it rendered things and client-side you had more JavaScript which rendered more things. It was cool. But the people making these simple apps were the artists who had JavaScript knowledge. I felt a disturbance in the force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years it manifested in a peculiar way. There was great angst against PHP and other less-cool setups. Not because they were bad, but because the people now working with the cool apps had no history with them. Making things was so cool that people didn’t care about re-inventing the wheel. You could say it was my first foray into the fight against populism. If I wanted to do something that had been solved potentially a decade earlier I had to write a lot of code as there was no standard library and once someone came up with a &lt;em&gt;module&lt;/em&gt; that did the thing, they became rockstars for blessing the crowd with this thing. It was very, very surreal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was even more surreal from the perspective of my employer, where, in production we value stability for web applications under very heavy load. There was nothing that Node.js solved. Additionally, we tried stresstesting a MongoDB database with our production data and it was bad. It just fell over. The promises of scalability were literally lies as queries took far too long and replication caused legions of new issues that were conveniently not documented really well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love progress and I &lt;em&gt;LOVE&lt;/em&gt; the Web 3.0 or whatever it is we now have with SPAs and whatnot, but the rabid frothing of the JavaScript community has lost all credibility. I’ve just been biding my time, waiting for a standard to emerge. Right now the standard seems to be Facebook’s React. It seems pretty cool. Like MVC-level of cool. Yet, it hasn’t cashed in on how to quickly make a thing. I’ve made several prototype apps but they are so small I haven’t been convinced what it actually solves, but I really, really want to. As a web developer who read all the news, I understand I must learn it well and I’m very much looking forward to mastering it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On paper I might sound bitter. No, ofcourse not. I am a professional and I do what I must. But in hindsight I do believe the people who came up with Node.js and those who were major players in the new ecosystem should have standardized a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of things. I was very disappointed in the io.js drama. Afterall, we all simply serve our customers and clients, and when starting a new project there should not be any ambiguity on how long your technology stack will survive before being deprecated in the name of pretentious progress. Maybe the enthusiasm would die down a bit if we had some way of measuring how much money is lost globally in unnecessary work caused by another broken piece in the gearworks. Long live left-pad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now coding, for fun: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A tiny React app for a “Friday bottle raffle”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A work-hours punch robot with a React interaface (an Electron-based Nightmare.js task runner)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Figuring out how to Reactize a Wordpress blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now coding, for work: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintaining an PHP MVC-app (Yii Framework)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing a theme for a Wordpress site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Enter 2017]]></title><description><![CDATA[Watching the events of 2016 and early 2017 unfold has been a very curious experience for me. Shocking but also rejuvenating, though for a…]]></description><link>http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/enter-2017/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/enter-2017/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2017 15:58:59 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Watching the events of 2016 and early 2017 unfold has been a very curious experience for me. Shocking but also rejuvenating, though for a slightly different reason than you might expect. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suffer from some kind of emotional detachment issues when it comes to society and the people around me &lt;em&gt;as a whole&lt;/em&gt;. It is maddening, really. In short, it’s impossible for me to see reason in forming a group for any purpose, be it political, religious, otherwise ideological or even stereotypical. If I squint hard enough I might be starting to see some light at the end of the tunnel, maybe. But first, let us observe the zeitgeist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is politics, anyway?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This strange emotional distance causes me to look down upon everyone who does take a role in some kind of group. I feel that anyone who does have some social group has “animalized” themselves, purposefully succumbed to a state where your own reasoning no longer matters favoring reasoning provided by someone else instead. For a long time I simply thought I was missing something, that my troubles while growing up had prevented me from seeing something others had seen. I tried to find myself by being politically active during my studies, but the more I tried the more &lt;em&gt;fake&lt;/em&gt; it felt. I started from the easily justifiable political left and trawled to somewhere in the center-right, visiting greens and pirates along the way. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ofcourse, in the end, none of it mattered. I was naive. People who are politically inclined towards some group will happily continue being in that group - they are invested in it both financially and socially and there is no use in trying to bring them to a better world which a competing group defines. Some people are “supporters” but most understand the game well enough to treat their group only as a means to and end, leaving emotions behind.&lt;br&gt;
Others, people who vote but are politically astray, will vote for the one that performs some stunt neat enough to win their vote. Responsibility for delivering promises is kept in the back of the voters’ minds as a testament for the futility of wishful thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, I see politics and other societal troubles as a interesting circus, where the parts of the groups who understand the game laugh at the society at the expense of those who don’t understand the game. Your choices are to join the game or become victim to it. It’s a game where groups mutually keep themselves in a pseudostruggle for power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the recent games of power, not just Brexit and Trump but even in my homeland Finland. Luckily, so far the local players here are smart enough to not let too brash players on the game board, but the whining of the world permeates all. The recent results of the votes were bred from a carefully cultivated sense of nationalism where insignificant issues have been amplified by careful adventures in the political games. Many jimmies have been rustled in an alarmingly short period of time. Not just the obvious nationalist anti-immigrant camp, but everyone taking part in the discussion, fueling it and watching the worlds burn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Longing for nothing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what’s the deal? You have this figured out and this sounds great, no? Observing people’s antics and patronizingly laughing from above - what could be better? Well, there is still the previous issue: I feel I am missing something that other people have. Thus, I guess I am jealous. I do not feel I am complete until I feel a connection to something. For the life of me I can not figure out what this could be. Humans are pack animals and inherently need a group. The inability for me to find something to socially relate to indirectly causes various psychological problems including, but not limited to, prolonged periods of depression and panic attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recent political movements are all just embarrassing madness, ofcourse, and I feel even more distanced from the crazy that drives this, but for the first time ever I feel something. I don’t know what I feel, though. I might defend my way of life, I might attack my way of life. I don’t know. But it’s a start.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Epic Lentils Gumbo]]></title><description><![CDATA[To kickstart my fabulous new blog I shall introduce you to one of the greatest and easiest recipes I know of. It was taught to me by an…]]></description><link>http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/lentils-gumbo/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/lentils-gumbo/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 16:31:11 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;To kickstart my fabulous new blog I shall introduce you to one of the greatest and easiest recipes I know of. It was taught to me by an amazing ex-colleague.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final product will be a “soup” which is thick enough to be eaten with a fork. It’s vegan unless you choose otherwise (sometimes I add cream cheese for taste)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will need:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1-2 red onions (or plain)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5-10 cloves of garlic (the more the better)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2-3 carrots&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3-4 potatoes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(other vegetables, like zuccini, cauliflower, broccoli, rutabaga, sweet potato, mushrooms etc. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;500g - 1000g mashed tomatoes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1-2 dl dry red lentils &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a splash of oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bouillon_cube&quot;&gt;a stock/broth cube/base&lt;/a&gt; or equivalent seasoning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spices: curry (lots), paprika (lots), chili, basil and others that float your boat (ginger, peppers …?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Do this&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heat the oil in a large pot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slice the onions and garlic and toss them in the oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add all spices in the oilgarlic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mix them for a while and let the onions soak it all&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After you’re satisfied, add the more “solid” vegetables (potatoes, carrots) first and stir them a bit, then add the rest of the vegetables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add half a litre of water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the stock cube, cleansed &amp;#x26; soaked lentils and any other vegetables that you might still have remaining. Add the tomato mash.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simmer on low heat for 30-60 minutes. Feel free to take your time (hours, even) - it just gets better, trust me. Stir once in a while to prevent anything from burning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have any fresh herbs for taste, add them last.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you take it off the stove and let it soak in, it will settle to a more solid form, if it’s not already.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>