<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[rapuhotelli]]></title><description><![CDATA[and the longing for nothing]]></description><link>http://rapuhotelli.net</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2018 08:31:58 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[So, you're a Full-Stack Developer]]></title><description><![CDATA[Every time someone says they are a “full-stack developer” I feel a sharp, nostalgic jolt up my spine. You might be one, but most likely you…]]></description><link>http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/full-stack/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/full-stack/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2017 16:20:13 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Every time someone says they are a “full-stack developer” I feel a sharp, nostalgic jolt up my spine. You might be one, but most likely you are not. Or, like me, at some point in time you were.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, a “full-stack developer” is a term used to describe someone who has the skillset to develop and deploy a product all on their own. For my kind of furious nerds who read every possible tech blog in a desperate attempt to understand what’s going on in the development world, being a full-stack is the ultimate goal. It means you are invincible. Today, however, it’s just too much. You have to focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in as recently as about 2010 (or so) being full-stack was relatively easy. The golden age of server-rendered MVC applications had just reached its peak. I got into Linux servers to study Apache and Nginx just get the satisfaction from the knowledge of being able to do it. Full-Stack back then was in essence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose our favorite MVC framework. Make some fancy-ass models, controllers and views. Extend a bunch of classes to be cool as fuck.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be proficient in SQL.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do some CSS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have access to a server which you can configure yourself to run your app.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you wanted actual scaling due to large amount of page views you needed special skills that were beyond full-stack. If you had to scale &lt;em&gt;shit got real&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you were poor you could have a server under your bed which runs your app (along with irssi and your torrents or whatever).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used PHP frameworks mostly and the choices were abundant. Early on I used something called CakePHP a lot, which &lt;a href=&quot;https://cakephp.org/&quot;&gt;still seems to be kicking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my studies I had a friend who had made his own &lt;a href=&quot;https://jonikorpi.com/less-framework/&quot;&gt;CSS grid “framework”&lt;/a&gt;. It was ace and I quite liked it. Sensible CSS toolkits didn’t really exist and the concept of bringing large-scale sanity into stylesheets had just barely been invented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hardest part was the server. The whole world of hosting was obscure as all hell, as it was really hard to find “tutorials” in a very academic unix world. Documentation existed, but applying that information to your needs was another beast entirely. You needed friends to show you the ropes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, we have the cloud. And not just the cloud, but today applications are far more complex. In my personal opinion, they are far more complex than is necessary. It’s a trap the industry has dug itself into, but that is a story for another time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting up a “full”, safe, and scaling web app is so much work that it’s very impractical to do on your own. The risk of misconfiguration is very high, especially in the cloud. Today, instead of being able to git clone an MVP and call it a day, &lt;em&gt;full-stack is a set of skills that theoretically enable joining a project in any part of the project.&lt;/em&gt; However, the details of that project are not necessarily yours to define, so it’s likely that your Full-Stack Developer would still lack a necessary skill. It all comes down to the near hysterical complexity of internet today. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s your typical considerations in 2017:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose your language and platform based on a bunch of conditions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the end result of the app? What are the performance requirements for page load speed and server capacity and how does it scale? Does it have to scale?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are your mobile considerations: make a separate mobile app or just “mobile first”? How well can it survive without constant supervision? Could you do that mobile app as well?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many people are going to be working on it and do they need to learn anything? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that the language and platform are chosen, decide on how your front-end should work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re doing client-side apps, what is the technology stack?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you prepared to start configuring webpack and Babel to get your anus destroyed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does your full-stackness involve UX competence or do you include &lt;em&gt;npm install bootstrap&lt;/em&gt; as a part of your expertise?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since you’re probably doing an API based app, we’re going to assume you daydream of OAuth specifications and GraphQL statements. Don’t forget to write your unit tests. We’re also assuming you know what database types to use and when.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re almost done. All you need now is to understand how the cloud actually works, and no, I don’t mean running an EC2 container with a bunch of dockerized things in it. In the traditional full-stack mindset you would also set up the pipes that build your cloudy container images for you with all the security groups and autoscales and all that. For me, this is the train stop where I get off. Maybe in the future I will handle this as well, but there is only a limited amount of hours in a day and I get my kicks from actual programming and product design. Sanity prevails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you notice that today we considered scaling and in the past we did not? That’s because how the application is developed and deployed is integral to how its scaling is going to work due to the inevitable continuous integration and continuous deployment setups which, ofcourse, are your job as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a reason why developers are in massive demand. There are so many possible end results and variations that no single person can do it &lt;em&gt;with confidence.&lt;/em&gt; All of the parts of modern web development have so much depth, and considering the historical context for the term “full-stack”, calling yourself full-stack in, say, job interviews should raise some flags. More than likely you don’t know what the word means or you’re trusting that your interviewer will gloss over the use of the term. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a weird topic to have strong opinions on, but I strongly believe you should just call yourself a “Web Developer” and then focus on your existing skillset and expanding your skillset. In fact, it’s rare that anyone involved with the web would focus on just one part of it. If you’re &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; confident about your experience, just use a Senior prefix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ofcourse, you’re free to defined the word as you see fit. Everyone does it, afterall. However, using the term properly is a good sign that you understand your profession and is considered &lt;em&gt;best practice&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The meaning of life, obviously]]></title><description><![CDATA[I asked a friend what should I write about next. “Talk about the meaning of life”, was the obvious answer. Let’s do it, then. Definition…]]></description><link>http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/meaning-of-life/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/meaning-of-life/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2017 17:32:39 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I asked a friend what should I write about next. “Talk about the meaning of life”, was the obvious answer. Let’s do it, then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Definition&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: this is in context of a westerner who lives in abundance as the question was asked by such a person. Different philosophical branches have a very different take on what is happiness and what is life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start with, life is not a toy you can buy so the question is not &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; is the meaning of life, but more like how to make life feel meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem of the meaning of life is quite easy to define, but associating yourself with the definition is the hard part. The approach I take is the approach of an utilitarian engineer. Go figure…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the whole picture:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are probably a human being, a pack animal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You were born without being asked if you wanted or not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of stuff happens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You will eventually die &lt;em&gt;probably&lt;/em&gt; without being asked when would you like to die.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is forced onto you and at the end you will die. I keep reading lame quotes where someone on their deathbed laments that the one thing they regret is something-or-other, typically not taking some opportunities or not seeing the world or whatever. I think having any regrets like this, or forcibly doing things in fear of having similar deathbed regrets is completely against the purpose of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply put, the meaning of life is to live your life and enjoy the ride. Cheesy, yeah, but the hard part is to make people realize how should they enjoy it, or to be precise, what should they be satisfied in so that they can take pleasure in that satisfaction. The challenge depends on the individual in question, but typically you can just ask: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are you satisfied with your daily life?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are not, why? What can you do about it? Why not?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, cheese, but let’s take a closer look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Demand&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average western person often sees their life as an empty shell. This is even more true today than ever before, now when internet dominates our social lives and social media completely saturates what we perceive of others and the society around us. I like to think that we have a &lt;em&gt;Demand&lt;/em&gt;, which is a constant. When you are a child you have a demand for simple things, but you feel very strongly about it. As you grow up, you still have demand but you learn to manage it. At some point you reach the point where your demand has only value in relation to the people around you. You have a job, hobbies, a spouse, friends, stuff. Still you demand but now what to demand is presented to you by your surroundings. Buy a car, gain status. Buy a house, gain status. Are you limited by money or other societal factors? You can always present yourself to others in such a way that you appear being something that the society would expect of you. Fear the stigma!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Demand makes you feel incomplete for the entirety of your life. Everywhere you look you see only things you desire - you learn to ignore the rest. I want to be that person! &lt;em&gt;He&lt;/em&gt; doesn’t appreciate what he has as much as I would, give it to me! I &lt;em&gt;demand&lt;/em&gt; a raise, I am worth more than this! For the majority of your life you are in a Demand state where the next step seems unreachable and you start asking these questions. What do I do with my life? How did I get into this mess? &lt;em&gt;What is the meaning of life?&lt;/em&gt; A person without Demand could be considered depressed and is “cured” once they able to reach for the next step again, demand just a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if something changes in your life and you fall down? It’s a shock. Something you depended on is no more and you are almost paralyzed and you cling on to the things you have, maybe reaching for support. Eventually you find a foothold in something and you feel stable again, but it’s far from where you left off. Still, you are satisfied, relieved. The world you came from seems distant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fall is often attributed to spiritual awakenings and other phenomena in which the person in question declares they now find meaning in their life - post-traumatically. I believe this is what everyone should look forward to. A similar effect drives all religions, politics and other movements. Recently only populism has started to move the average masses whose Demand is not movable by their own merit. Other movements just do not have the personal connection required to shake the Demand at its core.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are an average western person who has it all but lack meaning of life, you have several options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make a radical change in your life to force the Demand out of hiding. This could be anything. Move abroad. Sell everything you have. Someone feels the safety of the home is choking their Demand and choose a divorce. You decide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn not to Demand. Visualize the path that took you all the way up to this point and fucking be happy about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accept the existence of Demand and embrace it, just understand that it exists and don’t let it dominate your life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Bonus!) Make the society enforce the Demand upon you. Go to war. Do some crimes and go to jail. Vote for chaos in your next election, etc. Arrange the society so that your primal desires become justified instead of irresponsible. (Not recommended, but seems to be popular these days).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, getting back to regrets: I don’t think you should regret anything. Remember that you will die. You will just die. Dying of old age is not a better or “less regretful” death than dying sooner. The only way dying of old age is better is that there’s a higher chance of not having your friends around mourning for you anymore, but even then you’re no longer there to care. Being old, lonely and miserable sucks ass and everyone should avoid it. Ask any geriatrician. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just live your life and Demand things that you know are reachable in order to have a steady supply of meaningful satisfaction to you and to you only [1]. Not to be confused with selfishness. “You cannot love others until you learn to love yourself” is a classic cheese but very valid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] I’ll probably come back later to how you would manipulate the Demand to your own benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS.
For the entirety of my life I’ve wished upon a force majeure that would bless me with choice #1 but that is really hard to arrange yourself. I’m somewhere between #2 and #3 as I feel I got started on an average life about 10 years after people normally do but that, again, is a story for another time.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Development for what]]></title><description><![CDATA[I watched Ryan Dahl’s presentation on Node.js back then. A friend linked it to me and said it was gonna be big. I understood it was going to…]]></description><link>http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/for-what/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/for-what/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2017 15:45:31 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I watched Ryan Dahl’s presentation on Node.js back then. A friend linked it to me and said it was gonna be big. I understood it was going to be big, just not how big it would become. Every developer has their own take on this story and this is mine. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the 2000s web development was… different, but also much &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; simpler to learn. There was a lot of hype on Ruby, which campaigned against PHP as being more hip. MVC frameworks were cool as fuck. They are still cool to me. I like OOP quite much. I’m an engineer by heart and OOP is very easy to understand and develop. Ofcourse, these days I know that for larger projects with multiple developers OOP easily becomes a giant clusterfuck, but that is a story for another time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole development world and ecosystem were very academic - it was just programming. You always used the tools and libraries that were carefully crafted and stable. When it came to things that had the slightest risk of misusing something, it was always clearly emphasized how to not make an insecure thing. At best people linked to academic papers on input validation and even how to structure HTML properly in a best effort prevent browser parsing bugs or JavaScript bugs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frameworks did a lot of magic JavaScript. You used the framework’s own classes to render things on the page and it magically rendered all kinds of baked-in form validators and all kinds of things, so you wouldn’t have to. If you wanted to AJAX something yourself, that was &lt;em&gt;rad&lt;/em&gt;. You’d make an endpoint using your fancy-ass framework and it might render HTML directly and your jQuery or whatever would paste that HTML onto the page. Cool as fuck. Someone crazy might have used just JSON responses and jQueried something into the page and they would be asked: “Why would you do this? Just let the &lt;em&gt;application&lt;/em&gt; render what you wanted.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked with people who were front-end developers. That was new. You had people who on purpose did not do “backend”, but focused on colours, layout composition and even &lt;em&gt;typography&lt;/em&gt;. Some even did some JavaScript. I let them do their thing, but it was the first time I encountered an interesting (today very common) phenomenon: something that was designed to present itself in a specific way was not actually very easily doable by the MVC application. You lost the academic control of the application to something abstract and took risks regarding the functionality of the application in favor of &lt;em&gt;art&lt;/em&gt;. That was crazy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here’s the thing: the so-called front-end developers were not interested in the application as such. As time passed they did more and more JavaScript, which was great. jQuery and such were amazing. Once Node.js launched, people rejoiced. A new movement arose where using some special service you could easily “deploy an app” which was written in Node.js and it rendered things and client-side you had more JavaScript which rendered more things. It was cool. But the people making these simple apps were the artists who had JavaScript knowledge. I felt a disturbance in the force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years it manifested in a peculiar way. There was great angst against PHP and other less-cool setups. Not because they were bad, but because the people now working with the cool apps had no history with them. Making things was so cool that people didn’t care about re-inventing the wheel. You could say it was my first foray into the fight against populism. If I wanted to do something that had been solved potentially a decade earlier I had to write a lot of code as there was no standard library and once someone came up with a &lt;em&gt;module&lt;/em&gt; that did the thing, they became rockstars for blessing the crowd with this thing. It was very, very surreal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was even more surreal from the perspective of my employer, where, in production we value stability for web applications under very heavy load. There was nothing that Node.js solved. Additionally, we tried stresstesting a MongoDB database with our production data and it was bad. It just fell over. The promises of scalability were literally lies as queries took far too long and replication caused legions of new issues that were conveniently not documented really well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love progress and I &lt;em&gt;LOVE&lt;/em&gt; the Web 3.0 or whatever it is we now have with SPAs and whatnot, but the rabid frothing of the JavaScript community has lost all credibility. I’ve just been biding my time, waiting for a standard to emerge. Right now the standard seems to be Facebook’s React. It seems pretty cool. Like MVC-level of cool. Yet, it hasn’t cashed in on how to quickly make a thing. I’ve made several prototype apps but they are so small I haven’t been convinced what it actually solves, but I really, really want to. As a web developer who read all the news, I understand I must learn it well and I’m very much looking forward to mastering it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On paper I might sound bitter. No, ofcourse not. I am a professional and I do what I must. But in hindsight I do believe the people who came up with Node.js and those who were major players in the new ecosystem should have standardized a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of things. I was very disappointed in the io.js drama. Afterall, we all simply serve our customers and clients, and when starting a new project there should not be any ambiguity on how long your technology stack will survive before being deprecated in the name of pretentious progress. Maybe the enthusiasm would die down a bit if we had some way of measuring how much money is lost globally in unnecessary work caused by another broken piece in the gearworks. Long live left-pad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now coding, for fun: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A tiny React app for a “Friday bottle raffle”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A work-hours punch robot with a React interaface (an Electron-based Nightmare.js task runner)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Figuring out how to Reactize a Wordpress blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now coding, for work: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintaining an PHP MVC-app (Yii Framework)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing a theme for a Wordpress site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Salarakas ja kasvuyritys]]></title><description><![CDATA[Haluaisin kertoa pienen tarinan. Varoitus: tarina on pitkähkö ja sisältää paljon juustoa. Ei juustoallergikoille. Kelataan maailmaa…]]></description><link>http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/secret-love/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/secret-love/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2017 15:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Haluaisin kertoa pienen tarinan. Varoitus: tarina on pitkähkö ja sisältää paljon juustoa. Ei juustoallergikoille.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kelataan maailmaa taaksepäin ~15 vuotta. Rapuhotelli (minä) elää hiljaista, yksinäistä ja syvästi masentunutta elämää. Rapu on elämäntapanörtti, koska muutakaan ei ole - paitsi internet. Elämme vielä sitä aikaa, että nörtismi on vahvasti stigmatisoitu ja internet on ainoa hauska paikka maailmassa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Itseasiassa, internet oli niin hauska paikka, että kaikenlaista tuli löydettyä ja tehtyä. Ehkä paras oli Dink Smallwoodiin uusi yksinpelikampanja jollain mystisellä C-derivaattakielellä, vaikka en tiennyt mitä on C. Pelien modaus oli hulvatonta.
Keksin myös käyttää rivinumeroihin perustuvaa tekstitiedostotietokantaa koti.mbnet.fi:ssä, koska en tiennyt mikä on tietokanta. Joku voisi sanoa, että olin ns. itseoppinut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elämäni muuttui, kun sain kutsun laneille. Meillä oli lanit pienellä lukioporukalla ja heidän lähipiirillään ihanassa suuressa omakotitalossa. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ne olivat ihmeelliset. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laneilla oli ihania nörttejä, jotka puuhasivat kaikenlaista älytöntä. Päivä meni virittäessä verkkoa kuntoon koska kaikilla oli eri versio Windowsista. Toinen päivä meni kun tyypit asensivat Windowsejaan uudestaan. Viimeiset päivät sähellettiin internetissä tavalla tai toisella. “Olisinpa yhtä vahva ja ylpeä, kuin nämä ihmiset.” Vuosittainen kokoontuminen oli vuoden kirkkaimpia kohokohtia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eniten resonoi kuitenkin yksi henkilö - kutsukaamme häntä Toukaksi. Tuokka osasi. “Hei katso öööö. Väsäsin tälläisen.” Ja siinä oli joku paska SVG-animaatio, täysin epäkäytännöllinen nginx-konffi (mitä) tai lämpöpatteri wlan-antennina. Toukan kanssa säheltämistä odotin aina eniten. Töiden kautta Toukka sai aina tietää jotain uutta kivaa, &lt;em&gt;teknologiaonanointia&lt;/em&gt;. Järjellinen työelämä oli tässä vaiheessa vain joku asia mitä tapahtui muille, onnekkaammille, ihmisille. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aikaa kuluu ja pääsin alan kouluun (AMK). En loppujen lopuksi oppinut siellä yhtään mitään, mutta kontakteja tuli pilvin pimein. Kontaktien mukana realisoitui ensimmäinen pläjäys motivaatiota ja ryhdyin tekemään pieniä keikkoja pienille yhdistyksille, yrityksille ja lähipiirille. Rahaa siitä ei tullut. Minulle riitti vain kykyjen valjastaminen johonkin järjelliseen. Samoihin aikoihin Toukka työkavereineen teki jotain päräyttävää: lähtivät lätkimään ja perustivat oman Firman! Ältsiä! Seurasin vierestä kuin läähättävä koira. Välillä käytiin uudella ikiomalla toimistolla neppailemassa ja pelaamassa jotain Ouya pelejä tai juonimassa mitä koodataan seuraavilla Assyillä, tai jotain. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Se resonoi. En ole koskaan kyennyt “fanittamaan”, mutta Toukka, uusi Firma ja työkaverit olivat jotain, mitä ihailin. He olivat kuin perhe, jonka jäsenet kaikki luottivat toisiinsa ja tekivät fantastisia kilkkeitä, mutta ennen kaikkea tekivät sitä työkseen. Ihailin pakahtumiseen asti. Käteen jäi kuitenkin jotain tärkeämpää: ymmärsin, että minäkin osaan tätä. Missähän minun pitäisi olla? Maailma oli pahasti sitä vastaan, että olisin missään, mutta unelmat jäi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opiskeluiden loppupuolella sain hetkeksi pääni pois perseestäni ja hain alan töihin. Parin epäonnistumisen jälkeen opiskelukaveri vinkkasi jotain paikkaa ja pääsin. Ensimmäinen konttorikoodauskokemus oli pieni kulttuurishokki, mutta se oli kivaa. Tein yhden virheen: hakiessani työtä olin nöyryyspäissäni räikeästi aliarvioinut itseni ja se aiheutti pientä sekaannusta, mutta sain sen kutakuinkin selvitettyä. Tiesin viimein mihin sijoitun ammatillisesti: koodaus oli kivaa, internet oli kivaa, elämä oli juhlaa. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Välillä Toukka kysyi puoli-ivalliseen tyyliinsä “Mmm no koskas sä haet meille mmmm?” Ja vastasin aina samalla tavalla: Te olette gurujen loppusijoituspaikka. Minulla ei ole teille mitään annettavaa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Töissä aika lensi. Ihmiset vaihtuivat, projektit etenivät ja työympäristö muuttui. Vastuuta sai niin paljon kuin pyysi. Riemukseni huomasin voivani täyttää roolin, jota ei aikaisemmin ollut. Kutsuin roolia mussupalleroksi. Edellinen elämä ynnättynä opiskelijapolitiikkavuosiin jätti sieluun tietyn tyhjiön: tyhjiön, joka halusi minun polttavani omaa energiani ympärillä pyörivien ihmisten viihtyvyyden eteen. Kehitin uusia perinteitä, rohkaisin ihmisiä uusiin tuuliin, järjestin säännöllisiä erikoisuuksia piristämään ihmisten arkea. Osa tapahtui siten, ettei ihmiset tienneet sen tapahtuvan. Leikin jonkinlaista konttorin hengetärtä. Säteilin ylpeyttä. Hieman itsekästä, tunnustan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eräs kerta Toukka ivasi jälleen: “Hae nyt vaan, hmmhmm.” Pysähdyin miettimään. Sitten se kolahti: minä en tarvinnut enää Firmaa hengelliseksi esikuvakseni. Jossain vaiheessa olin saavuttanut pisteen, jossa luottamus omaan ammattitaitoon oli viimein niin vahva, että tiesin itse missä mennään, miksi, ja osasin jopa argumentoida sen puolesta. Rakkaus Firmaa kohtaan säilyi, tietenkin, mutta tunsin että minut oli nostettu johonkin, jossa tunsin olevani kotonani. Konttorikoodaamista on jo tehty monta vuotta ja harrastuneisuustausta on erittäin pitkä. Mitä jos nyt oikeasti hakisinkin Firmaan? Mitä sitten? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ymmärsin, että koko ammatti-identiteettini perustuu siihen, että tämä yksi gurukokoelma ovat kuin rokkitähtiä jotka näyttävät minulle tien. Minulla on esikuva, joka on aina edellä ja heidät on turvallista pitää lähellä. En usko että olisin ilman Toukkaa töissä missään. Koodaus on niitä ainoita asioita joista nautin ja uskon olevani Toukalle kaiken velkaa. Mitä jos hakisin ja he ottaisivat minut? Where is your God then?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entä mitä jos hakisin ja minua ei huolittaisikaan? Se olisi kuin pyytäisi koko aikuiselämän kestänyttä stalkkauksen kohdetta treffeille ja tulisi torjutuksi - mitä helvettiä minä sitten tekisin? God is dead. Pystyisinkö säilyttämään rakkauteni? Uskallanko edes ottaa sen riskin? Vaikka kulttuurisopivuutta en epäile hetkeäkään (ei ole käynyt edes mielessä ennen kuin tätä kirjoittaessa), teknologiat etenevät niin järjetöntä vauhtia, että en yksin pystyisi viettelemään mitenkään. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En vain tiedä. Ehkä sitä pitäisi ottaa taas hetkeksi pää pois perseestä. Viime kerrasta kun on jo monta vuotta. &lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Enter 2017]]></title><description><![CDATA[Watching the events of 2016 and early 2017 unfold has been a very curious experience for me. Shocking but also rejuvenating, though for a…]]></description><link>http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/enter-2017/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/enter-2017/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2017 15:58:59 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Watching the events of 2016 and early 2017 unfold has been a very curious experience for me. Shocking but also rejuvenating, though for a slightly different reason than you might expect. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suffer from some kind of emotional detachment issues when it comes to society and the people around me &lt;em&gt;as a whole&lt;/em&gt;. It is maddening, really. In short, it’s impossible for me to see reason in forming a group for any purpose, be it political, religious, otherwise ideological or even stereotypical. If I squint hard enough I might be starting to see some light at the end of the tunnel, maybe. But first, let us observe the zeitgeist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is politics, anyway?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This strange emotional distance causes me to look down upon everyone who does take a role in some kind of group. I feel that anyone who does have some social group has “animalized” themselves, purposefully succumbed to a state where your own reasoning no longer matters favoring reasoning provided by someone else instead. For a long time I simply thought I was missing something, that my troubles while growing up had prevented me from seeing something others had seen. I tried to find myself by being politically active during my studies, but the more I tried the more &lt;em&gt;fake&lt;/em&gt; it felt. I started from the easily justifiable political left and trawled to somewhere in the center-right, visiting greens and pirates along the way. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ofcourse, in the end, none of it mattered. I was naive. People who are politically inclined towards some group will happily continue being in that group - they are invested in it both financially and socially and there is no use in trying to bring them to a better world which a competing group defines. Some people are “supporters” but most understand the game well enough to treat their group only as a means to and end, leaving emotions behind.&lt;br&gt;
Others, people who vote but are politically astray, will vote for the one that performs some stunt neat enough to win their vote. Responsibility for delivering promises is kept in the back of the voters’ minds as a testament for the futility of wishful thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, I see politics and other societal troubles as a interesting circus, where the parts of the groups who understand the game laugh at the society at the expense of those who don’t understand the game. Your choices are to join the game or become victim to it. It’s a game where groups mutually keep themselves in a pseudostruggle for power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the recent games of power, not just Brexit and Trump but even in my homeland Finland. Luckily, so far the local players here are smart enough to not let too brash players on the game board, but the whining of the world permeates all. The recent results of the votes were bred from a carefully cultivated sense of nationalism where insignificant issues have been amplified by careful adventures in the political games. Many jimmies have been rustled in an alarmingly short period of time. Not just the obvious nationalist anti-immigrant camp, but everyone taking part in the discussion, fueling it and watching the worlds burn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Longing for nothing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what’s the deal? You have this figured out and this sounds great, no? Observing people’s antics and patronizingly laughing from above - what could be better? Well, there is still the previous issue: I feel I am missing something that other people have. Thus, I guess I am jealous. I do not feel I am complete until I feel a connection to something. For the life of me I can not figure out what this could be. Humans are pack animals and inherently need a group. The inability for me to find something to socially relate to indirectly causes various psychological problems including, but not limited to, prolonged periods of depression and panic attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recent political movements are all just embarrassing madness, ofcourse, and I feel even more distanced from the crazy that drives this, but for the first time ever I feel something. I don’t know what I feel, though. I might defend my way of life, I might attack my way of life. I don’t know. But it’s a start.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Epic Lentils Gumbo]]></title><description><![CDATA[To kickstart my fabulous new blog I shall introduce you to one of the greatest and easiest recipes I know of. It was taught to me by an…]]></description><link>http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/lentils-gumbo/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://rapuhotelli.net/2017/lentils-gumbo/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 16:31:11 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;To kickstart my fabulous new blog I shall introduce you to one of the greatest and easiest recipes I know of. It was taught to me by an amazing ex-colleague.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final product will be a “soup” which is thick enough to be eaten with a fork. It’s vegan unless you choose otherwise (sometimes I add cream cheese for taste)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will need:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1-2 red onions (or plain)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5-10 cloves of garlic (the more the better)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2-3 carrots&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3-4 potatoes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(other vegetables, like zuccini, cauliflower, broccoli, rutabaga, sweet potato, mushrooms etc. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;500g - 1000g mashed tomatoes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1-2 dl dry red lentils &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a splash of oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bouillon_cube&quot;&gt;a stock/broth cube/base&lt;/a&gt; or equivalent seasoning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spices: curry (lots), paprika (lots), chili, basil and others that float your boat (ginger, peppers …?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Do this&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heat the oil in a large pot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slice the onions and garlic and toss them in the oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add all spices in the oilgarlic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mix them for a while and let the onions soak it all&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After you’re satisfied, add the more “solid” vegetables (potatoes, carrots) first and stir them a bit, then add the rest of the vegetables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add half a litre of water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the stock cube, cleansed &amp;#x26; soaked lentils and any other vegetables that you might still have remaining. Add the tomato mash.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simmer on low heat for 30-60 minutes. Feel free to take your time (hours, even) - it just gets better, trust me. Stir once in a while to prevent anything from burning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have any fresh herbs for taste, add them last.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you take it off the stove and let it soak in, it will settle to a more solid form, if it’s not already.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>